you're listening to the AI native Dev
brought to you by
[Applause]
[Music]
Tesla hey there Simon Maple here today
on the AI native Dev we welcome a
crossover episode from our friends at
the infr Pod a podcast all about
software infrastructure by Timothy Chen
and Ian Livingston now guy Pani was a
guest on the infr Pod recently and he
discussed the tessel vision and AI
native development generally and also
how through the abstraction of natural
language the future of software
development is far more accessible to
many many more developers than ever
before so I hope you like the episode
welcome back to the Pod this is Tim from
Essence VC and let's go Ian this is Ian
Livingston lover of Dev tools and
infrastructure uh and I'm super excited
today we're joined by a good friend of
mine guy padour who is currently on his
next company Journey CEO of tessle
former still founder of sneak guy could
you give us a little introduction to
yourself oh thanks team andan for having
me on here I'm yeah I'm gujar or Geo
someone said I'm pulling a Madonna with
the other one name I am I indeed founded
sneak I founded Blaze before that and
sold it to AK I was CTO there for a
bunch of years before founding sneak now
I'm the founder and CEO of tessle trying
to reimagine software development I'm
sure we're going to talk about that a
fair bit more here and I couldn't help
it I'm an active angel investor I've got
a little bit over a decade about a 100
Angel Investments love the learnings and
excitement that I felt from learning
from all these other Founders and yeah
that's me also a lover of Dev tools a
nerd and geek about many topics
including Dev and AI you've been at it
with blaze since the very beginning
right like 2011 2010 and before that
right which watchfire like you worked at
watchfire I think as well so you been
here from the get-go in terms of the
main take on the industry and you've
seen a lot of the different sort of like
phases of evolution as well so I'm super
excited my main question though is Geo
what is it that you saw that you said
you know what I'm going to go and start
another company yeah I think this is a
question every multi-time founder gets
you're on company three now so what is
it that made you say after especially
after the successive sneak like what
made you say you know what this is the
moment where it's time for me to go get
back at it I get in the trenches and
start from zero again yeah it wasn't an
easy decision the sort of the push and
pull maybe of it on one hand on the
personal front I spent the last year and
a bit at sneak in a slightly more
part-time function trying to figure out
what it is that I do I started sneak and
I was CEO and they brought about five
years in brought in Peter McKay who's
done a great job and I focused oruk the
sort of the product strategy role in
there and then after a bunch of
excitements and period of time I really
felt like I need to reassess what is it
that I'm doing in the company and what
is my role and so on one hand I had my
sort of personal Journey we have a
family charity try to figure out do I
want to do that full-time I'm doing
Angel investment do I want to do that
full-time do I want the comfy life of
sort of some part-time job in a company
I believe in and then promoting and
during that time came to realize that
what I want to do is found another
company and I was resisting that
conclusion it doesn't make sense from a
practicality perspective we're going to
donate all the sort of the funds they
still have at sneak as we're doing where
like I've got all the whatever access
and such that I need so there's really
no practicality to it so it took a while
to realize that it's okay to do it
because that's what I want to do and
that's where my passion came to this
realization that satisfaction comes out
of struggle if you want to feel that
satisfaction to feel that meaning then
you have to put yourself into a thing
you might fail in and while I learn a
lot from these Journeys with engine
investing and such it's not the same
when you don't own it when you're not in
the trenches anding to do it and I guess
alongside that I was focusing a lot on
Snak AI strategy and Snak secures
software development and so if you want
to figure out what should Snak do about
AI you have to have some hypothesis
about uh where is software development
going because snake's roll very much
relates to that and the more I dug into
that and the more the little picture
crystallized in my mind the more I felt
I want to build that that's what I want
to do it also felt like a domain that
matched my skills my passion but was not
competitive to sneak and so yeah the
combination of those two me make the
leap and I will say my wife figured out
that's what I'm going to do probably a
good couple of months before I did I
wanted to talk to her about it a little
bit more she was like with a smile
saying yeah go ahead talk it's leading
sure let's talk about it and here we are
that's incredible I've gone through some
of that myself as well and I always come
back to builders just want to build and
how do you enable that yeah was there
some insight though that you saw as well
around at the time that you were
thinking of starting the company and
making this transition working on the
sneak AI strategy what did you see what
you were learning that said okay this is
different this is an opportunity to do a
generational shift like I'm sure now
third time founder you have learned a
lot about what to look for in terms of
okay there's a big potential opportunity
here that I can grab on to is like what
built up over that time that led to you
saying okay I see the generational shift
or I see something I attached to that
gives me an opportunity to do something
that's rewarding it is going to be
really difficult but the upside is there
whether it's personal or financial this
point there has to be something right so
I'm really curious to understand is was
there some unique Insight or some unique
specific observation that got you to
like okay this is the place I'm going to
make the BET yeah and I think first of
all like what drives me is impact in
terms of is it money is it sort of
product it like really I think what
motivates me is leaving a dent on the
universe and doing something that I
think is significant I felt like with
sneak we've done that there's a lot to
still build on the business a lot to
still do but I feel like a core part of
that mission of getting security more
embedded into development and making
that be a norm of good practice in
development like I think a lot of that
is achieved and so the driver is impact
and I saw a lot of things you mentioned
like funding multiple companies several
times like I learned a ton from that
process but I also learned a ton from
Angel Investments and from working and
accompanying those Journeys someone has
told me that as a Founder you learn in
sequence and as an investor you learn in
parallel I think it depends on your
level of involvement with the companies
and all that and I think the combo at
least for me proved very useful in
building some pattern recognition and
seeing things that work and don't work
and I guess what I've seen also through
the angel Investments because I was
investing in AI Dev tools and such one
is people are very short-term minded I
think AI is full of that there's just so
much opportunity to use AI to improve
things that people are drawn to the
immediate two is that things are just
startups are just not differentiated you
you look around and we talk to two
companies they're doing it it's like
they're really the same and they have
all these like false perspectives of how
they will differentiate they're talking
about hey will have a data mode really
you're going against an incumbent you're
going to be around for a year doing this
maybe you got seven customers maybe 70
customers and yet somehow you will have
a data mode to an incumbent that has
70,000 of those and and so poor
differentiation strategy for like where
would you build it even if you are
temporarily differentiated very
short-term orientation and I felt like
everybody was just thinking small and
the ones that were thinking big from a
tech perspective not a product
perspective you look at all the top
companies
like in terms of big names in the AI Dev
space and the ones that are really like
the go big players they're very Tech
first versus product first companies
magic Dev cognition poolside not to
diminish like I think these are amazing
companies and amazing individuals
building them but my sense is that for
the most part they are building amazing
technology and then out of that building
the product and I'm a product guy I
think about what is the product that is
needed how do I anticipate users
changing how do I anticipate ecosystems
and markets change from there I build
technology in service of the product and
so I felt these gaps were there the
long-term orientation thinking big
thinking product first they were all
lacking and then strong differentiation
and I guess I had an answer to all of
those right like the picture that formed
in my mind felt like I have a sense of
what is the long-term destination how to
build something towards it that is good
from a user perspective and that would
be sustainable not all of it is stuff
that I can share here on the podcast and
some of those are still strategies that
are in house but without that I think
founding an AI company right now is
actually more risky than founding a a
company is in the generic sense because
everything is changing the landscape is
shifting from under you everything is
overfunded and so it's actually a higher
risk than typical so I think you already
alluded to these topic I'm very
interested to really go down this rapid
hole as far as we can which is really
about this AI native developer theme or
we even call transformation right
because I'm reading really the two big
block posts you put out one is like AI
native almost like a native developer
and there's also like the cloud native
comparison so maybe we'll start with the
AI native
developer like transformation here you
put up a 2 by two Matrix right comparing
like the existing tools and existing AI
almost products and tools and tesel is
on a far
rights this new category that there's
nobody else is there right just you and
I think it's intriguing everybody read
this will be super intrigued including
me and I'm sure Ian as well and we
really don't know what does that mean of
course I think you have like you just
alluded to you have strategies in your
head so maybe it can help normal and
bystandard uh developers like us can you
help us maybe give us a little bit
mental picture of okay how did you maybe
can you quickly summarize that what this
2 by two is because I think a lot of
people haven't really read that post
perhaps right how do you think about the
world and give us maybe that somewhat of
a hint of okay the current tool set
isn't the truly Paradigm Shift we're
looking for what could it be right maybe
we can start a little bit from that but
I think maybe you can talk about this
magical 2 by two I think will be very on
a good start here yeah so I will say
this 2 by two and I published it under
that title of charting your AI native
Journey so AI native is is dominant in
its narrative is something that I've
been brewing on and evolving in my mind
over the last really almost two years of
exploring Investments and thinking about
ideas then eventually a tessel and of
course it's sneak there are many AI
Solutions out there and indeed some of
them are short-term long-term and they
oscillate between something that feels
like wouldn't this just be the next
feature of open AI or anthropic or
whatever to things that feel like
science fiction no this will never work
and so the attempt here with the 2 by
two is to give us a little bit of a
structure to place companies or at least
current offerings of companies within
that and so the two way to goes with two
Dimensions one is a dimension of change
so how much does this new tool require
me to change the way I work to use it
and then the second dimension is one of
trust it goes from from attended to
autonomous how much do I need to trust
it to get it right for it to be useful
so let's maybe look at some examples in
the the different quadrants here that
this creates right if you draw it as a
graph on the bottom left what you'll see
is the low change low trust environments
and those are tools that are very easy
to slap on in the dev space that might
be code completion you're already typing
right you're literally already typing in
fact you're already familiar to Auto
completion because of intellisense and
such and so it's just a better auto
complete you eyeball it you say if it's
correct or not you just continue There
pros and cons to that but still very
easy very low trust other domains it
might be something that points out a
potential problem on an X-ray or that
writes a quick SDR like cold Outreach
type email all of these things are like
they're small units they are things
you're already doing and therefore
you're just prompted this is the sort of
the bottom left quadrant the low
friction why wouldn't you use this it
needs to be useful so if it doesn't
provide business value if it doesn't
work well enough it's still worthless if
it does work then why wouldn't use it it
just makes you better that's the high
adoption category as I see it uh and
it's massively comp itive that's really
where you would see how is one coding
assistant better than the other coding
assistant like you're going to have a
million of them how is one tool that
creates tests for me or that captures
the documentation or like all these
things like how is one different it's
oftentimes hard because they don't
really invent any new methodology
they're just doing leg work and they're
doing leg work in small units so you can
review them so that's the sort of the
button lift if you go up the trust route
that's really an IP Evolution it goes
from attended to autonomous first maybe
examples of what needs to show up over
there so for example intercom have Finn
their support chat bot and Finn tries to
resolve tickets when someone approaches
a company autonomously if a human has to
review every response that Finn provides
to confirm that it doesn't hallucinate
anything the product would be useless so
you have to trust that it gets it right
for you to be useful even more extreme
version of that is Robo taxis like
actually very little change nothing
changed you're still interacting as you
before interacted with someone on a chat
support conversation here in robot taxes
you might open your Uber and and order a
a taxi and get in the car and get
dropped off elsewhere but might the high
trust that you need to be able to do
this so that's up the trust route in
development world that's a lot about
this autonomous development world and I
think it hasn't been cracked and that's
a lot of what I think the sort of the
magic devs or the others like at least
from outside statements are trying to
crack I will just resolve this for you
and it's worth realizing or highlighting
that there's an element of the magnitude
of task involved in that trust element
right so if you're writing the next line
of code I can review it every single
line but if you are writing full
applications I can't review them every
time so for you to be useful to me I
need to trust that it works and if not
then it doesn't serve the use case
you're trying to get me to believe that
it does right or a lot of workflow
Creations so I think a lot of this
autonomous AI
engineer whatever AI Dev AI engineer is
now loaded and I'm being term right but
agent engineer a lot of those are really
up the trust axis and because they're
trying to do things more autonomously
and I'll say again that this is an IP
game and so if you're a company and
you're trying to build over there it's
because you believe that there's an IP
mode that is really hard to replicate
and I think in general Now versus two
years ago I think conviction that you
can have a true IP mode in AI
implementations is different I think two
years ago you might think that people
are they can really be ahead of the game
and now you see that every time someone
is ahead they're just three months ahead
or six months ahead but you still hear
like you hear a cursor for instance
which is you know a different type of
company talking about how all they need
to be is ahead on the Lex Freedom
podcast by a few months and that can be
significant so that is their strategy is
to try and remain ahead which I find to
be a challenging strategy like you still
aspire to that but it's hard for that to
be your strategy so I guess that's a
half I don't know if I fit the briefly
comment but that's half the the quadrant
yeah yeah and I think it's a very
helpful overview because I think a lot
of people we probably intuitively know
about it but what's helpful about it
almost like a mental model is it really
helps you think about the existing world
and of course it's very helpful to think
about what your new world you're
proposing and exactly yeah I know we're
not able to get into the details of teso
obviously about the product because
things are pretty early but I'm very
interested because I think this whole
new IP transformation and like high
trust to be able to generate High trust
it almost requ requires like this trust
earning Journey the product needs to
require to get and maybe hold that
thought a sec let me talk about the
change route and then we come back
precisely to that to the journey so like
the trust route like you go into that
car and you need that trust and there's
a trust building exercise maybe you'll
take shorter rides once it's small maybe
you would only do it after a friend of
yours took it right like you might do
all these things but it's still the
trust route I think the bigger harder
path is one of change so change is about
changing the way you work and I think
probably the best analogy there is the
text to video or text to image
presentation so I'm a fortunate to be an
investor in Synthesia Synthesia is text
a video solution that focuses on
training and things like that one of the
leaders in the space and the way you
create the video in Synthesia is
entirely different to the way you would
create a video pre a there's really
nothing in common about how you would
set up a studio and get actors and shoot
with a video and all that and how you
would write that text and because of
that that is dramatic change in who is
it that would be able to operate that
successfully what are the skills what
are the workflows in the business that
you would build and there's effectively
zero chance that the winner in the AI
generated videos will be the same
companies that are the ones producing
the videos in person today but the
difficulty over here is when would you
start using it and how would you use it
and Synthesia have actually figured out
a good specific Niche or sort of slice
so maybe that's a demonstration of a
joural around these training videos that
already were very methodical in the
different languages and such but when
you go and you go to to Runway or you go
to the more loose form Generations how
do you generate a video in that fashion
there are new problems that you would
need to deal with that are brand new you
don't really know how to overcome them
around character inconsistency suddenly
a different person you don't get that
problem right when you're shooting a
video and suddenly a doppelganger of an
actor shows up instead of the original
actor someone similar but not quite the
same and so so these are new problems
they new workflows but if you succeed in
building a new way that is truly better
and and text video is a good example of
one in which there's like massive
advantages if successful it's like
dramatically cheaper and faster then you
can unlock tremendous value and you can
really win that space and so I think
that's really the disruption Corner
that's the place in which you can really
rethink an industry but the Slowdown
Factor isn't just trust it's change and
people are slow to change and so I think
you can develop IP faster than you can
get get people to change and it's
actually quite hard if I bring it back
to development it's quite hard to think
about what does this mean in development
I think a little bit of that is this
notion of chat-based creation and so
everybody immediately gets the code
completion but you'd find conflicting
and sometimes hostile opinions about
generation with chat because that's a
new way of doing it it's a different
methodology how do I do I talk about my
document like how do I work with that
and so it takes longer to adopt maybe
it's better maybe it's not but it takes
longer to adopt and it's a difference I
think the vzero or the sort of the
bootstrap of an application this way
again it's a different way of doing it
so it gets you somewhere is it the right
where is it the right starting point
what do designers think about it some of
them have very kind of vicious opinions
about them and some of them are in love
with it and so I think that change route
is interesting and then let me just
quickly talk about the top right which
is really just a combination of those
and to an extent in what you refer to
when you talk about how you to build a
trust that's the hardest quadrant that's
s of the top right it is a new way of
doing it and assumes trust and so really
at the moment if you just build for the
top nobody would use it you require them
to change and to trust at the same time
it's just not going to happen but
eventually every company should
understand what is its top right
positioning if you're going to build a
company acquire a company to any domain
you have to have a thesis about what is
in the top right because that is what we
will eventually have is when the techn
is trusted and whatever useful changes
are there to be had they have been
adopted and so we'll get back to Tesla
and a native development but what we're
talking about in the ative development
model is let's start by imagining the
top right and then there will be many
Journeys to get there but you have to
agree first directionally about what we
think that top right is and you have to
have that be a lively conversation and
have a lot of people engaged and try
things in it and all that for us to be
able to kind of form that destination
and if all you're building is for the
bottom left you might get some immediate
dollars but your compan is going to
become invalid or
irrelevant short answer but it was a
great answer the way I think about this
a self-driving car model right many ways
like the assisted sort of driving cruise
control is a good example of a co-pilot
fully self-driving car we still have to
have I have this thing on my Subaru or
if I have my hands on the wheel the car
will drive itself but I'm still like
there and then there's the full
self-driving version which like Tesla
you can just do whatever you want and
then in future you have obviously the
robo taxis like if anyone's been a weo
that is incredible and that though if I
were to think about like the AI native
future in development would be like the
weo version of whatever software
development is one of the things I think
about is today the example is the
co-pilot the auto completion or or the
chat basically like this change in how
The developable Works inside the IDE and
so we've seen 50% speed UPS what do you
think an example of an AI native future
for a software developer looks like is
there like a mental model you have or
like a gap in experience that you've
been thinking about that demonstrates
the difference between I'm driving a car
and I always I have my eyes on the
odometer and the car in front of me to
oh now the taxi is like driving me
around have you thought about what that
could look like first of all it's
interesting that in the self-driving car
there are actually examples of two big
companies that are taking different
Journeys to it weo is taking the IP
route and they're very much they have no
co-pilot you're jumping straight into
self-driving they're only graduation is
like the distances or the cities they
operate in while Tesla is taking the
assisted driving rout and trying to
evolve their features like that and time
will tell what's better and they might
both be viable but they're very
different so it's interesting like these
are two Giants and they're both taking
very different routes to it I think the
software analogy to self-driving cars is
a little bit tough because self-driving
cars have a physical limitation and so
you can't really make a self-driving car
10 times faster right or you can make it
much better in various ways and over
time you can create a reality that is a
100 times better if there's no parking
lots anymore and all that space Cas has
been reclaimed by cities and there are
fewer accidents and car ownership
becomes a non-issue because everybody's
just reusing these cars and so you can
imagine a better future but the driving
itself the Driving Experience is shorter
I think for software development there's
actually a better opportunity because
you can both improve the journey itself
where like get from point A to point B
by 100x and you can improve the
ecosystem and the totality of it by
another factor that is simp
maybe I can talk a little bit about what
I think is a native development does
that make sense that'd be amazing yeah
again I think this is a a group
definition right like you know a
community it's a new paradigm and we
need to work together as a community to
doing it and just point out as a bit of
a plug that we do have a conference that
we're funding and operating and all that
but with a lot of kind of bright
opinions about it that is running what I
think would be late the week that this
airs on November 21st called the AI
native Devcon and we're going to have a
lot of bright speakers over there
talking about all sorts of aspects of
entive development but with that said
let me talk a little bit about our
definitions I think software today
software development is very code
Centric you get some requirements you
write some code very quickly you make a
100 decisions in the code that never
make it anywhere else or it might be too
low resolution they might have not been
bothered to go out and the code
intertwines what needs to be done with
how to do it it's like literally in the
same lines you you read the code and you
need to parse out what is it doing and
how is it doing it and separate the two
and the llms that try to learn the code
they need to do the same and I believe
that we will move to a world that is
spec Centric in which uh we can separate
the two and a user can specify what they
want which is not a trivial problem and
AI will handle the implementation in
that world uh where AI does the coding
and the implementation there are many
things that suddenly become dramatically
better for instance AI native software
will be autonomously maintained
maintenance by definition is change the
software without changing the spec keep
it behaving the same way but change the
operating system change the dependency
fix that vulnerability but don't change
the spec and so if you start from
anchoring on the spec and have good
verification mechanism to know that the
software is working correctly you don't
need to maintain that anymore and
maintenance is like the productivity
killer so that alone is like massively
valuable it is dramatically more
accessible because there are just that
many more people that can specify what
they want and can be the judge of that
and even think architecturally sometimes
but uh are not able to write code it
would be very adaptable to your
environment so you'd be able to create
software that you know on Ian's
infrastructure is optimized for that and
on Tim's infrastructure is optimized for
their environment or that learns from
the data and operations of how your
specific users are using the system and
your specific business needs right are
you flush with cash and you're really
looking to provide the best experience
and you want to optimize for latency and
such or are you more worried about costs
and trying to do it or maybe different
times a day you want different things
right for different users and like an
extreme level of adaptability and
personalization and automation can be
there it can have a deep relationship
with data I read some stats that I'm not
sure if it's uh coherent but it aligns
with my general thinking which is that
software generally uh is thought that it
can be 10,000 times faster if you really
fully squeezed and optimized every
aspect of it but that's expensive
because like human time is expensive but
maybe with AI if you're tied to it so
it's just better on so many fronts and I
guess our conviction is that building
software like that being able to specify
what you want being able to provide and
then evolve the verification mechanisms
to know to trust that the software works
the way you want and then thinking about
how that software works over time like
thinking about how do you write the
specification how do you write the
verifications how do you edit those
future versions of it how do you package
those how do you version something like
this this is language agnostic you can
have a JavaScript version a python
version of it are they the same version
how do I think about them what happens
if they have some language specific
ecosystem change on it is that a new
version for both how do you observe a
system like that how do you know what
has occurred and so all of those require
a different software Factory they
require a different development Paradigm
in methodology and they require a
different development platform form what
we're perceiving here and we can go into
each of these paths deeper if you'd like
is that on one hand we think this is a
new development paradig and we think
this is software development and a lot
of the answers like we will not be the
ones thinking about them and they will
also not have one answer both because of
the complexity of software and the world
so it could be that the way you would
verify a mobile game is just very
different to the way you would verify an
e-commerce site and to the way that you
would ver an internal in-house
application or any of these others but
also because it's not going to be app
point in time right like it will change
now maybe in some magical world figured
out all the ways to doing it like over
time different organization context but
also new technology comes along things
change there are opinions and multiple
ways to do it and so we think this a
native development this is a methodology
and it has some like in devops like in
cicd there are some themes that are
recurring there are some practices that
span ecosystems but there are many tools
and they plug together and they work
together and so we think there's an
importance for a Dev movement around it
which is why we're running the
conference which is why we're looking to
build and help Foster a community around
what is an development what is that top
right for development and on the other
side on the company side on the product
side is we're trying to think what does
a development platform for that look
like how do you write those specs how do
you advance it and how do you plug tools
along the way clearly to build a product
it has to be usable can be dependent on
something else so it's useful in its own
right but how do we think about that as
something that facilitates the
participation of others versus excluding
them yeah so that's my view on AI native
development and I've got many more I can
drill into any of these things I think
they're all kind of deep topics yeah I'm
sure we can have a 24-hour podcast
because it is actually really exciting
the more you mention it it gets a little
bit clear what you're actually trying to
achieve and you think about the future
like you mentioned about w
once you're able to actually fully trust
that this car can actually get you from
point to point B your whole life changes
potentially right the whole rules and
everything around changes a lot I think
definitely it's really exciting to think
about the future development if we can
fully trust a particular spec that is
actually able to encapsulate what we
really want to achieve then the Imp
implementation details may not matter as
much but of course the biggest challenge
is the spec it's the creation
maintainance
and the sort of iterations and the Team
Dynamics around the spec right and I'm
sure there's so much details and
probably wble to go to most of it but
you already mentioned there is this
specification of what it does and a
specification of how it verify it
actually does the correct things and
there's so many things in between can we
talk about I'm very curious about the
spec aspects what are the major
challenges to make sure a spec can do
what it does because right now when I
think about it we gone from test driven
developments right all these little
small little Paradigm shifts of trying
to make sure we're getting the right
thing to be delivered and but none of
these are coverage enough right and
cannot keep up with the changes and all
the complexity behind the systems so
it's really hard to imagine there's a
speck that can actually take care of
everything so is your uh particular mind
or pattern or even challenges we have to
overcome when it comes to actually
figure out how to get the spec correct
cuz I think that could be something to
highlight right this this is not easy
thing at all here's actually really hard
things we had to figure out along the
way yeah I think yeah and I would add so
I think everything you say is correct
it's hard to imagine this type of spec
and I'll share my thoughts in a sec I
would also add how do you make it fun to
write s respect if it's an agonizing
process it might be functional but if
it's not fun people are not going to do
it and so not only does it need to be a
powerful spec it also needs to be one
that is fun to create or it's a process
that makes it fun to create it there are
actually two reasons why I think we'll
move to spec Centric development the
first one is probably most obvious which
is machines can write code now but the
second that is as important if not more
is that machines can fill out the spec
if I tell an nlm create a tic tac toe
game that's a spec it's a pretty
terrible spec but it's a spec and the
reason it's a spec is because the llm
can fill in the gaps it can decide
whether it's a web game or a mobile game
it can decide whether it follows the
rules of tikto and what are those and
whether it's there's a multiplayer or
machine and hopefully in the smart
system it can interact with you and know
when to ask you questions as well and
say tell me do you want this to be a web
game or a mobile game but one way or the
other it can figure out which questions
to ask and it can figure out how to fill
out the spec and I think that is a
massive unlock that allows us to break
this mod that we have today we have
either formal specifications which are
such a nightmare to write that they they
only make sense in the most sort of
harsh conditions where you really have
to have that right when it's a deep
device or Aerospace and even there
they're limited but they're very painful
to write you prefer from an experienced
perspective to just write the code or on
the other side you have no code which
are toys like they're really smart
configurations all the activity all the
ideas have been pre-created and now
you're just choosing how to organize
them and in watch flows to run them and
so it's always been very limited and as
they evolve they become code like in
Apex in Salesforce so I think the
ability to fill in the gaps is really
the unlock that llms introduced that are
as important if not more important than
the ability to create code and the
ability of the system to fill in the
gaps correctly is going to be one of the
strengths of specific platforms as they
come in so if you're a marketing agency
and you've already built five websites
for me and I'm coming to and I'm asking
you to build the sixth website I only
need to give you a very small spec
because you're well familiar with me
you're well familiar with the domain and
you'd be able to fillm in the gaps very
well but if I try to come to the same
individual and I I'm asking to build a
mobile game for me I might need to give
you very detailed specifications if
you're some sort of lowcost agency that
I'm engaging that I've never worked with
before for the same marketing website I
might need to provide very detailed
specifications and so I think the
ability to fill in the gaps is very
important so that's sort of one
important bit about the spec the second
is that I don't think there is a spec I
think there will be multiple specs once
again the way you would specify a mobile
game is probably very different than the
way you would specify or a software
library right or a marketing website
there will be shared traits but if it's
more visual you might need something
that's more visual if it's very
algorithmic you might need an ability to
provide those and it comes back to me
thinking about this as a movement as a
paradigm as an ecosystem like today we
don't have one like we have multiple
languages we have multiple development
environments we have methodologies that
are different around their sort of
strengths and weaknesses is it more
about iteration or is it more about
safety and I don't think that changes in
the AI era you everything becomes faster
but you still need to choose your
tradeoffs you still need new platforms
and systems that are able to adapt to
new technologies and to new preferences
and to the industry's preferences and so
I think there will be multiple specs I
think they will have many formats
verification is a subset of the spec
because it comes back again like same
statement right the way you would verify
a mobile game is different than the way
you would verify you know an algo
trading system than the way you would
verify a marketing website and so you
need these verifications there I don't
have a perfect answer to it I think the
ability to stated is is important and
tdda helps us and like mocks help us and
a bunch of history of what we've been
building helps us I would also point out
that just like regular software it
doesn't have to be upfront and there's
an element of learning from data and do
you build a system that works well
enough and that you engage with well
enough and then with the data that
system can learn and can evolve and can
become better over time and yeah a bunch
of interesting topics here for instance
if you said I want a button and the llm
decides that button will be red and you
might be I don't really care it's fine
it's if the button is red or it's blue I
don't really care but for the next
version that comes along you change the
title you might not be okay with button
changing now from red to blue and so you
might want some visibility into the llms
decisions and into the Persistence of
them and whether they're about to change
or usability and so all of those are the
reason we think this requires a
different software Factory these are not
the types of problems that exist today
in the regular Tools around software
development they're not just another
file in your git repository they're not
just another test in your build they're
different types of interactions and we
think they need to be figured out some
longed answer here it's a longed answer
but it really helps I think it really
helps me a lot to be honest like fully
understand sort of your thinking one of
the things I wanted to like zoom in on
is you've talked about this being a
community effort and so like a mental
model for comparison of the cloud wave
right that you know the 2010 to let's
say 2020 period was what we collaborate
on ultimately like the sort of runtime
operating system of movement the cloud
became kubernetes right that was the
thing that became the community the core
part of was at the core of everyone
stack everyone kind of contribute around
it with attachment to the GitHub and
some type of cicd so talk still okay
there's some core pieces of software
there's some core Community movement and
that Community movement is represented
by some shared platform that we're all
building on top of I'm curious in your
mental model is the spec like a
community thing is that company
proprietary what parts of this of the
sort of this community movement do you
think are let's say process methodology
so we all believe that the future of
software development is this way and
describe this manner in the same way
that like the agile Manifesto kind of
describe a shift from waterfall to to
Agile method in software development and
what parts do you think need to be ore
software that I collaborate upon like
things that just occur in the open
source I think it's just a combination
of many of those I don't think spec is a
single standard I think there will be
multiples so some specific specs will be
company specific and will probably be a
bit more closed they might have to be
like maybe sap has their own
specification methodology that has to do
with their systems right and specs might
compose over time right and connect
different formats so I don't know I can
tell you all of the above but I think
spec is a higher level comment it's like
saying it's all code owned by I think
there will be multiple standards and
some will not be standard and some will
wish they were standards
others a not so I think those will
evolve but I think Community
collaboration even in the cloud is
actually much bigger than what you've
described yes we we might have settled
on kubernetes but before that maybe
there's a settling on containers and
what about microservices and what about
mesh networks and how do they interact
between them and what about API
standards and how those communicate what
about licensing for software maybe
that's even an active discussion yet
about hosting something on the cloud
versus not right about access
permissions and IM models now and
jumping like a Bastion hosts so there
are all these things that really have
evolved as a community when I think
about Cloud I don't just think about
specifically the infrastructure as a
service I think about cicd and
microservices and devops and the whole
way that we develop software that has
changed dramatically there are
methodologies there that are continuous
like you can say generally the best
practices frequent deployments or
frequent small builds that get deployed
and ability to roll them back not
everybody achieves it all the way but I
think it's generally accepted as the
ideal you want immutable infrastructure
is desirable not everybody invests in it
because it has some cost and sometimes
effort observability is a thing you
should have and so there are practices
that are part of a high level best
practice that has evolved and then there
are specifics that are ecosystem
specific or just opinions if you talk
about observability many opinions if you
talk about cicd and even maybe my
comment about frequency talk about monor
Repose versus small Repose and it's okay
it's thriving it's the way progress
happens um so when I think about my
perception of say cognition with Devon
or you know many of these sort platforms
they're closed environments they maybe
more the the Microsoft of old saying
come into our world Garden they might be
building something that's very powerful
but I don't think that's the thing
that's stend the test of time and so
that openness comes both from an open
methodology from some open source
components which I think have to exist
and from pluggable and composable
infrastructure so I host a podcast
called the AI native Dev I'm not very
creative with names I had the secure
developer before and now the a native
Dev I guess that's what happens when you
build Dev
movements and I had a Matt Billman from
netlify the CEO and co-founder of
netlify on it and he made a really
interesting point around how every new
technology Paradigm challenges the open
web or the openness because they really
drive you towards those environments you
see this with mobile and you see this
with I guess with the internet at the
beginning sort of the chat systems and
social networks today and he points out
that I think we're going to need to deal
with that now you're saying I think in
Matt's case he was referring maybe more
to the versel versus the nfy reality I'm
not sure I'm putting words in his mouth
here but okay do we build these as
features of an ecosystem where is it
that we build this as collaborative
capabilities in favor of the open web
I'd like that to continue and so I think
there's a big evolution there I I want
to say something if my answers weren't
long enough I've got something
additional to add to it that wasn't even
in the question which is I think
eventually this notion of software
creation that becomes so easy because
you just request what you want and
you're able to interact with the system
and it gets to learn you so it fills in
the gaps I think it becomes like
literacy and so the end goal here which
is far it's far but the end goal here is
really for software creation to be a
thing that is just accessible to anyone
right I think the two of you and like
many developers listening to the uh
podcast probably experien like
encountering some annoyance in their
day-to-day life and solving it with
technology or building whether it's a
hobbyist thing or just a small solution
or something some app for themselves and
you want that to just be accessible to
just be a tool that everybody has to
solve their problems and so I do think
that there's long-term significant
importance over here and so above and
beyond all of those productivity boosts
and whatever commercial advantages I
think there's a societal element over
here when you say that I think it
becomes even further clear why it's
important for this to be remain open and
remain connected and not be just a
platform so while I'm building a
platform that I hope will be the leading
platform in this domain I think it's
critical that it is a leading platform
in an open domain amazing I think you
already got to close to what we actually
want to go for the next section which is
the spicy future spicy
Futures so as we want to hear sh your
hot take about the future I'm very
curious what is your spicy hot take
maybe about this whole AI native
developer what is some things you
believe that most people don't believe
in yet maybe the one like that is a bit
spicy to people is that I think coding
goes away it's one of those things that
I I think many people don't want to
believe because coding is fun I love
coding coding has this sort of video
game mentality of like you can always
level up right you get a task you do it
you complete it it's you get your
endorphin hit on it you can always level
up or you can do the same level it's
amazing so super super fun and seems
like a little bit unfortunate to go away
but I think coding goes away coding is
also the translation layer to the
machines and it is limiting Us in so
many ways I don't know precisely the
timeline but I think its effect happens
faster than we think this is a world in
which progress happens in leaps not in
steps and I don't think I am advising
anyone who is currently a developer to
really re evaluate their life choices I
think there's going to be work for a
while for many times but do I want my
kids to focus now on learning how to
code as a core competency five years ago
I would have said coding as literacy I
would have really talked about that for
the same goal that I've mentioned right
now I don't think so now I think coding
as a skill is a short-lived skill it
would remain a hobby it would remain a
specialist skill but it would not be a
prevalent skill I don't know maybe in a
matter of a decade something like that
maybe 10 to 20 years maybe a decade is a
bit too too fast I have an opinion here
but I'm curious what do you think the
limiting factors are today in terms of
reaching that reality what's holding us
back what are we missing from the tool
set what are the core fundamental
problem that we have to isn't solved
today but needs to be solved for us to
to actually get to this spec based
future where anyone can write code and
the same way that anyone can write in a
word doc they can go and open word doc
and type it and it can help lead them
through it I assume that's a version of
it or a possible future yeah I'm really
curious to understand what you think is
is limiting us what are we missing there
must be some fundamental problems we
have to solve to get there yeah you need
the Tesla platform to launch on the no
maybe there's something a bit more
active I think I do think though it is
the change in the trust that are the
axis and both of them just need to
evolve so on one hand the tech isn't
there this is at the edge of the
possible today LMS are too unreliable
too hard to Wrangle and get to do what
you want they're quite limited I think
they're evolving very rapidly and so
this will change but they are not there
today and it's a bit hard to State
that's why I've used the bigger numbers
because it's hard to say whether
significant progress where gp5 arrives
in a year or in five probably not more
than that or at least that's a decent
guess but it might take a while and then
the second probably the bigger slowdown
factor is that of change and the notion
of how do we interact with code like
that and some of that is making the
system work to the assumptions that we
perceive to be necessary today so like
we're very used to machines being
deterministic to tell it something it
does the thing you want and by the way
like people that are less technical
often times don't have that expectation
they've encountered the finiki machines
and for many of them one or the other it
is Magic it works or it doesn't work and
the computer doesn't let me do this is a
common perspective but still some of it
is like getting the new machines to
behave to our expectation and some of it
is learning how to adapt our
expectations sorry for referring to yet
another sort of episode in the in the
but like I spoke to Caleb Sima who's a
big security guy love his thinking and
we had this interesting conversation
about how to think about security
scanning in the lens of AI if you have
an ability to scan your software and it
does let's say typically does a better
job at finding vulnerabilities that are
there and not giving you alerts about
vulnerabilities that are not there two
times out of 10 or one time out of 10 it
misses things or it just hallucinates
code hallucinates Codes like maybe for
false positives are okay but let's just
say misses things so you have code it's
been blessed you've deployed it to
production and it turns out it just
forgot to tell you about something orate
all in all I think that's a better
system if it's better enough in its
accuracy but it's weird it's require
really rethinking how do you do the
methodology for security I think there
are just many cases like that so if you
go further into the society and into
people that are not coding today that
changes even slower because you also
have to remove fear and you might need a
generation you might need the kids that
sort of grow up with this type of tech
and build them out on top of that
there's regulations and there's other
things but change society humans they're
the Slowdown factors not the tech and I
think we actually didn't really talk too
much about tesel I know everything is
early I think we got to the point now
you're working on something about spec
and you're working something around the
community maybe tie a bow here what is
Tesla how do you want to describe Tesla
today to our audiences and I guess you
were talking about the conference that's
probably one big way for to learn about
your community
but what will people wait to start
getting to learn more about your product
as well yeah tesel is two things maybe
like on one hand we are looking to be a
driving force and getting this community
that we call the AI native Dev and
there's the podcast check in to tune
into to that join the conference on
November 21st and we're going to have
more and more activities to just
facilitate this conversation right get
people thinking far ahead because so
much of the conversation today is about
today and by the way a lot of the tools
of today are useful facilitat ERS of the
conversation but tomorrow how do you
like when you think about test you think
about documentation generation some
tools I think are a little bit less so
code completion that's maybe a little
bit less the other part of Tesla the
primary part of Tesla maybe is the
platform so what we're building is we're
building a platform for AI native
development we want that platform to be
open and usable by many and so we're
building it with that line site it
doesn't work yet it's a it's still
closed what you can do is you can go to
tesla.app enjoyed the wait list and we
hope as soon as we can to make this uh
to get more and more people in to
produce software in this fashion what I
will say is it's a new paradigm and it's
big and I'm a believer that you have to
get the product out there and give users
the opportunity to tell you that it
sucks so that you can ask them why and
you can fix that and you can evolve it
and in the case of a new development
Paradigm and platform it takes a while
to build even that mvp but it's still
that mvp that we're going to build at
the beginning and so what I would say is
if this is interesting if you want to be
part of what is the future of software
development if you want to be a voice in
it join the community learn about it
share your opinions and such if you want
to try out what I think will be the
first and hopefully one of the key tools
in the domain then join the weight list
and hopefully try out the product and
just the expectation is we want the
early adopters it's going to have some
things that you'd say wow this is
awesome and it's going to have something
is going to say well this sucks and I
guess our hope is instead of just
renting about it or shutting your
browser window and returning again uh
you tell us this sucks and work with us
to fix it I'm I'm super excited to play
around with it myself I've been waiting
for almost a year so it's G to be a good
time I have one question we have a lot
of like entrepreneurs or W toe
entrepreneurs that are trying to figure
out what to do I'm curious as you build
Tesla and as you thought about this do
you think this wave the shift to AI
native software development do you think
this is a wave of creative destruction
that results in many new companies or do
you think this is a wave that basically
becomes like an enduring advantage the
existing incumbent I'm curious how you
think about that because there's lots of
people who are very excited about Ai and
there's an opportunity from my
perspective to reinvent a lot of how we
think about software development and
always represents an opportunity for new
company creation and new category
creation so I'm curious for those
aspiring folks that are looking to go
start or looking to join a new company
how's your mental model there in terms
of is it this a thing that's going to
really reward incomin or is this a thing
that is like a creative destruction
that's going to enable us to reinvent a
lot of stuff yeah I think the
trust
AIS is more in favor of the incumbents
because like fundamentally it boils down
to building IP it boils down to having
data to be able to optimize that IP and
so you can potentially win there but I
think mostly if you're talking about
something that's at the bottom left or
going up the trust taxes then I think
you're better off thinking about this as
an acquisition all you're doing is
you're outrunning the big companies
because it's still bigger and you're
trying to be friendly to them and they
might acquire you and the numbers are
big that's a legit strategy for people
finding a company it's not interesting
to me as someone founded sneak and looks
to something big but it's legit that you
know you could say that's what I did
when my first startup it wasn't as
intentional but it worked out and put me
in a good place to start sneak so that's
one path the change path I think is
still favorable to the disruptors and I
think the mistakes that people make or
the most common mistake that people make
as they found company is that they don't
think longterm enough and this is just a
very fast moving space and so you have
to have a view view that is a bit
contrarian that is a bit hard to believe
if everybody nods when you tell them
about the story something is missing
something you're not thinking far out
enough and so I I do think that there
needs to be some boldness and some
long-term path but I think that change
the same dynamics that always exists
remain it is the existing players the
existing incumbents they control the
existing workflows and it is in their
best interest to maintain these existing
workflows as long as possible and
everything about those companies is
wired to maintain it of course some of
them will manage to break out of the
innovator dilemma so this counter
positioning path but most won't and so I
think those are the opportunities to go
after they're scarier and they are
harder and as I said I think starting a
company in the AI space right now is
actually higher risk than than typical
but I think the only two kind of truly
viable paths are one is build a company
that outruns the big companies in a plan
to be acquired
or build something that's a bit wild and
that goes further out some of this is
true in general like when I Angel invest
today Investments later then account the
leaps of faith and clearly if you talk
to a company and you need to have 10
leaps of Faith so figure out whether to
invest in or not is a problem but if
there are zero that's a problem that to
me is like a bad it's like something
here is obvious and in the world of AI
it probably means there's like 100
reasonably funded companies that you
just you haven't heard of them because
they're too small they're like you right
right there might be there hasn't been
enough time for any of them to become a
player but rest assured there's funding
there are smart people and there's a lot
of attention and so more companies will
be around so you have to have something
a bit wild a bit contrarian that of
course you believe in you're not just
like creating a a funky tail if you're
committing your time to it for it to be
worth it and I guess maybe like the
other advice that I would have is
another common saying that I have for
Founders is nobody cares about your
product they care about the problem that
you're solving for them and so in the
world of AI you have to think about
problems that will become greater over
time that there are real problems and I
think a lot of people find problems
today in the AI ecosystem those are the
high execution mode like it's obvious to
many people that those are problems they
might be solved by the platform might be
the Pix and shovels things so it's
really an execution game over there if
you want to win that but I think the
interesting ones is to think about okay
what would happen when legal reviews are
very common or are done so much more
easily because of AI the judicial system
collapse so should I build something for
judges that sort of does this but what a
bias or maybe what happens in the Pharm
I don't know whatever it is that is in
your space think about it from the lens
of understand the ecosystem understand
the pains anticipate the best you can
what would be the pains that evolve here
then try to figure it out once again
many leaps of Faith here you have to
have some conviction in it you have to
be convincing about that but then you
can build a sustain
kind of long-term differentiated company
amazing I guess last thing for audience
where can we all follow the center of
all AI developer movement which is guy
and Tesla what social channels or places
people should sign up so for the company
it's a tessel doio you can also go to AI
native
dev. I love the doio domain I find that
represents development too so although
we bought the a again it's not about the
fact that it's AI it's about the fact
that it's a development so we routed
there me personally guy pjar at there's
fortunately pjar is sufficiently
uncommon that you can find me on the
twitters and the LinkedIn and I'm
probably most active on LinkedIn and so
if you follow me on LinkedIn that's
probably best we do have a newsletter as
well so if you go to Tesla Doo you'll
find yourself either able to register
the newsletter or join the conference or
you can sign for the weight list all of
those are good cases to be involved lots
and lots to discover and I think pass
inting conversations like you can be a
believer you can be a non-believer you
can think the path is not but I've yet
to really find anybody that doesn't
think the conversation is interesting
awesome thank you so much guy this has
been really insightful and Tim and I
really enjoyed it and uh I think this is
a great one that we've done so I hope
you have a I can't wait for the a native
Defcon to be honest thank you thanks for
having me on
[Applause]
thanks for tuning in join us next time
on the AI native Dev brought to you by